Guide to the Thomas C. Brogan Papers on the Mayor's Task Force on Civil Disorder, 1968 AIS.2017.06
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thomas C. Brogan Papers on the Mayor's Task Force on Civil Disorder
1968
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Brogan, Thomas Cyril
AIS.2017.06
0.42 Linear Feet
Thomas C. Brogan, a student of political science, was a member of the Task Force on Civil Disorder created by Pittsburgh Mayor Joseph M. Barr following the civil unrest in April of 1968. This collection of papers includes reports, memo's, interviews, and statistics used by the Task Force in their fact-finding mission.
Access Restrictions
Folder # 45 entitled, "Confidential list of names of people interviewed" is restricted and sealed until 2040. There are no other restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Thomas C. Brogan, Ph.D on March 14, 2017.
Scope and Content Notes
The first series consists of topical files that contain an assortment of reports, memo's, lists and academic papers that where presumably used by the Mayor's Task Force as source material for a final analysis of the events leading up to the civil unrest that happend in Pittsburgh between April 4th and 12th in 1968. The second series contains findings from interviews conducted by Dr. Brogan on behalf of the Task Force. Only one interview contains an actual transcript, all the rest are abridged findings. Unfortunately, the papers do not include the final report of the Task Force.
Biography
Dr. Thomas C. Brogan is a retired professor of Political Science at Albright College in Reading, Pennsylvania. Brogan graduated from LaSalle College with a Bachelors Degree in 1966, followed by a Master's Degree in 1970 from the University of Pittsburgh, where he was a National Defence Education Act Fellow. He completed his Doctorate at the University of Pittsburgh in 1976.
In 1968, while at the University of Pittsburgh, Brogan was awareded an American Political Science Association Fellow in local government, enabling him to work in the administration of Pittsburgh Mayor Joseph M. Barr. During that time Pittsburgh, like many cities around the United States, experienced a period of civil unrest following the assination of Dr. Martin Luther King. From April 4 through April 12 rioting broke out in several Pittsburgh neighborhoods including Manchester, Homewood-Brushton, and Hazelwood, but the Hill District was perhaps the area that experienced the most violence and distruction. Following the unrest, Mayor Barr created a Task Force on Civil Disorder.
While working in the Mayor's office, Brogan was assigned to work with Kenneth Mason, a brother of City Councilmen Louis Mason, to research the causes of the unrest and recommend actions that local government could take to address priority issues in the Black community, as part of the Mayor's Task Force on Civil Disorder. The Task Force was chaired by Burrell Cohen, the executive secretary to Mayor Barr, and included two members of Pittsburgh City Council and four city employees. Research began within a few weeks of the riots and would continue into the summer of 1968. In July of 1968, a final report was issued. Ultimately, the main issues that were recommended for local government to address were centered around housing, business opportunities, and jobs.
According to articles in the daily newspapers the report was met with some very vocal opposition. Perhaphs the most well-know opponents were Byrd Brown, President of the Pittsburgh Branch of the NAACP, and William Rodd of the Neighborhood Centers Association in Manchester. Pittsburgh Civil Rights attorney and noted activist, Eric Springer was serving as the Chair of the Mayor's Commission on Human Relations. Although, Springer was interviewed concerning the Task Forces' findings, his comments in the press were not disaproving nor passing judgement.
Related Material
Governor Dick Thornburgh Papers, AIS.1998.30, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System, Series II: Early Legal Career, Box 12 Folder 27 -- "Administration of Justice during Civil Disorders in Pittsburgh," A report by Public Service Committee May, 1968.
Charles Owen Rice Papers, 1935-1998, AIS.1976.11, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System, Box 4 Folder 36 -- "A Commentary on the Report of the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders," by Arden E. Malzer (University of Pittsburgh), Prepared for the Human Relations Commission of the Diocese of Pittsburgh.
Allegheny Conference On Community Development (Pittsburgh, PA), Records, 1920-1993, MSS# 285, Detre Library and Archives, Heinz History Center, Box 311 Folder 6 -- "Mayor's Task Force on Civil Disorder, 1968."
Previous Citation
Thomas C. Brogan Papers on the Mayor's Task Force on Civil Disorder, 1968, AIS.2017.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in two series.
I. Topical Files
II. Interviews by Brogan
Civil disobedience; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Race relations; Mayor's Task Force on Civil Disorder (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Mason, Kenneth W.; Barr, Joseph M.; Brogan, Thomas Cyril
- Topical Files, 1968; I.
  - Aerial view of Pittsburgh and the Hill District, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arrest Statistics between April 5 and April 12, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ralph W. Conant (Brandeis University), "The Conditions and Factors Underlying Community Tensions in Pittsburgh", undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ralph W. Conant (Brandeis University), "Six-City Study A Survey of Racial Attitudes in Six Northern Cities: Preliminary Findings", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Focus A Community Publication for the Northside, June 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Governor's Branch Offices, Statistical Summary, June 1, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hill District Recovery Program-First Priority Actions, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - List of demands from the North Side, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memo by Commander William H. Moore (Bureau of Police) to Director David W. Craig (Department of Public Safety), regarding "Evaluation and Assessments of Civil Disorder in Pittsburgh from April 4, 1968 to April 12, 1968", April 26, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memo by Superintendent James A. Cortese (Bureau of Building Inspection) to Attorney Cy Fox (Law Department), regarding "Extra Money Costs--Civil Disturbances", April 10, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Neighborhood Youth Corps, Questionnaire, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - News Release, Statement by Mayor Joseph M. Barr to City Council, July 3, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Presidents of Neighborhood Committees, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Progress Report, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Proposals for the Task Force, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Resource Committee, Preliminary Factual Statement of Chronology of Recent Disorders, May 24, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Elayne Rosen (University of Pittsburgh), "Report to the United Jewish Federation Board, 'The Urban Crisis,'" including a list of businesses that were destroyed or damaged in the Hill District., June 18, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Statement by John Turner, Executive Vice President of the Hill District Citizens' Committee on Economic Opportunity, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Statement by the President of The Forum to City Council, May, 17, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Testimony by William H. Rudd II (Neighborhood Centers Association) and Richard P. Ridenour (North Side Community Action Program), June 7, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sidney Z. Vincent, "The Double Dilemma: An Exploration of the Jewish Communal Responsibility for Jewish Survival and for Social Amelioration", April 4, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Interviews conducted by Brogan, 1968; II.
  - List of Questions, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Interview #1--Community leader from the North Side, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Interview #2--Politician from the Hill District, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Interview #3--Psychiatrist working in the Hill District, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Interview #4--Hill District community member, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Interview #5--Religious leader in the Hill District, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Interview #6--African-American leader interested in employment opportunities for the A-A community, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Interview #7--African-American female who is active in community afairs in the Hill District, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Interview #8--Member of a Catholic Religious Order and active in United Black Front, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Interview #9--City employee, former minister and active member of the Brushton community (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Interview #10--Social service work on the North Side, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Interview #11--African-American policeman, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Interview #12--Job counselor for Neighborhood Youth Corps, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Interview #13--Lawyer and a member of the Urban League, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Interview #14--Executive with the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Interview #15--Two members of Community Action in the North Side (one African-American, one white), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Interview #16--Small business women who is active in community affairs in the Hill District, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Interview #17--African-American businessman in the Hill District, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Interview #18--African-American female who is active in community affairs, especially housing (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Interview #19--African-American religious leader in the Hill District, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Interview #20--Staff members of the Hill District office of the G. P. O., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Interviews with Arrested Persons, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Interviews with Presidents of Neighborhood Committees, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Confidential list of Names of people interviewed [RESTRICTED--until 2040], undated (Box 1, Folder 45)